Guide to the Montana Department of Health and Environmental Sciences. Licensing and Certification Bureau Records 1947-1988
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Health and Environmental Sciences, Licensing and Certification Bureau Records
1947-1988
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 108
Montana Department of Health and Environmental Sciences, Licensing and Certification Bureau
5.5 linear feet of shelf space
The Licensing and Certification Bureau of the Montana Dept. of Health and Environmental Sciences inspects nursing homes and other medical facilities for compliance with standards, in cooperation with the United States Health Care Financing Administration. Records (1971-1986) consist primarily of survey files.
The Montana Department of Health and Environmental Sciences was given the responsibility, under the 1967 Session Laws, to license hospitals, long-term care facilities, nursing homes, and related institutions. Included in this function are the approval of new facilities, expansion of facilities, changes in classification, and inspection for adherence to standards. The Health Services and Medical Facilities Division and its Licensing and Certification Bureau also act as the agents for the United States Health Care Financing Administration in approving health care facilities for Medicare patients. Among the reasons a health care facility's license or Medicare approval can be revoked are failure to meet minimum standards of construction and fire safety, failure to provide sufficient medical staff with the proper qualifications, conviction of a felony by the hospital manager, mistreatment or neglect of patients, and financial inadequacy. Licensing and Certification Bureau staff inspect each hospital, nursing home, and home care agency on a regular basis. Any inadequacies in significant areas of performance have to be corrected before the license can be renewed.
Records consist of survey case files (primarily 1971-1986) on hospitals receiving Medicare payments, nursing homes, long-term care facilities, and home health care agencies. The files include licensing survey reports (1971-1979), pink copies listing deficiencies found on regular surveys (primarily 1982-1986), and records of the facility's correction of those deficiencies. In addition there is some correspondence between the facilities and the staff of the Licensing and Certification Bureau and of the Health Services and Medical Facilities Division. A few folders include material, such as incorporation papers, bylaws, etc. dating back to 1947.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Hospitals--Home care programs; Hospitals--Inspection; Nursing homes--Inspection
Montana; Government and Politics; Medicine and Health
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Case Files
  - Anaconda: Area V Home Health Agency, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Anaconda: Community Hospital, 1969-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Baker: Fallon Memorial Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Big Fork: Big Fork Convalescent Center, 1972-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Big Sandy: Big Sandy Medical Center, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Big Sandy: Sande Convalescent Home, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Big Timber: Pioneer Nursing Home, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Big Timber: Sweet Grass Community Hospital, 1956-1966, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Billings: Deaconess Hospital, 1970-1984 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Billings: Glendeen Nursing Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Billings: Montana Youth Treatment Center, 1985 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Billings: St. John's Lutheran Hospital, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Billings: St. Vincent's Hospital, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Billings: Valley Convalescent Nursing Home, 1972-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Billings: Western Manor Nursing Home, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Billings: Yellowstone County Visiting Nurse Service, 1966-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Billings: Yellowstone County Nursing Home, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Boulder: Boulder River School and Hospital / Montana Developmental Center, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Box Elder: Rocky Boy Health Board and Home Health Agency, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Bozeman: Bozeman Convalescent Center, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Bozeman: Deaconess Hospital, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Bozeman: Deaconess Hospital Home Health Care, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - Bozeman: Gallatin County Home Health Agency, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - Bozeman: Gallatin County Rest Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Bozeman: Medical Staffing Center, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Broadus: Powder River Nursing Home, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Browning: Blackfeet Nursing Home, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Browning: Browning Home Health Service, 1974-1985 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Butte: Beta Factor Home Care, Inc., 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Butte: Butte Convalescent Center (formerly part of Silver Bow General Hospital and Nursing Home), 1974-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Butte: City-County Home Health Services, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Butte: Crest Nursing Home, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Butte: Highlands Hospice, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Butte: Park Royal Convalescent Center, 1975-1987 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Butte: St. James Community Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Butte: Silver Bow General Hospital, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Butte: Southwest District Public Health Nursing Service, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Chester: Liberty County Home Health Agency, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Chester: Liberty County Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Chinook: Sweet Memorial Nursing Home, 1968-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Choteau: Teton Memorial Hospital, 1950-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 16-17)
  - Choteau: Teton Nursing Home, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Circle: McCone County Hospital and Nursing Home, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - Clancy: Hillbrook Nursing Home (formerly Alhambra Manor), 1971-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - Columbia Falls: Montana Veterans Home, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - Columbus: Stillwater Convalescent Center (also known as Four Seasons Nursing Center), 1974-1985 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - Columbus: Stillwater Home Health Care, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
  - Conrad: Pondera County Home Health Care, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
  - Conrad: Pondera County Hospital, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
  - Conrad: Pondera Pioneer Nursing Home / Pondera Medical Center Extended Care Facility, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 26-27)
  - Culbertson: Roosevelt County Home Health Care Agency, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 28)
  - Culbertson: Roosevelt County Memorial Hospital and Nursing Home, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 29)
  - Cut Bank: Memorial Hospital / Glacier County Memorial Hospital and Nursing Home, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 2 / 30)
  - Cut Bank: Outreach Professional Home Visits, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2 / 31)
  - Deer Lodge: Colonial Manor, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Deer Lodge: Montana State Hospital, Galen, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Deer Lodge: Powell County Home Health Care, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Deer Lodge: Powell County Memorial Hospital, 1966, 1971-1988 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Dillon: Barrett Memorial Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Dillon: Barrett Memorial Hospital Home Care, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Dillon: Parkview Acres Convalescent and Nursing Home, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Drummond: Granite County Home Health, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Ekalaka: Dahl Memorial Hospital and Nursing Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Ennis: Madison Valley Hospital, 1954, 1966-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 10-11)
  - Ennis: Madison Valley Nursing Home, 1978-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Eureka: Mountain View Manor Nursing Home, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Forsyth: Rosebud Community Hospital and Nursing Home, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
  - Fort Benton: Chouteau County District Hospital and Nursing Home, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Fort Benton: Chouteau County Home Health Agency, 1985 (Box-folder 3 / 16)
  - Glasgow: Frances Mahon Deaconess Hospital Home Health Agency, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
  - Glasgow: Frances Mahon Deaconess Nursing Home, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
  - Glasgow: Valley View Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
  - Glendive: Dawson County Home Health, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 20)
  - Glendive: Eastmont Training Center / Eastmont Human Services Center, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 21)
  - Glendive: Glendive Community Hospital and Nursing Home, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 22)
  - Great Falls: Cascade County Convalescent Nursing Home, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 3 / 23)
  - Great Falls: Columbia Hospital, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 24)
  - Great Falls: Columbia Hospital Home Health Care, 1967-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 25)
  - Great Falls: Deaconess Hospital and Rehabilitation and Nursing Home, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 3 / 26)
  - Great Falls: Deaconess Medical Center Home Health Agency, 1966-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 27)
  - Great Falls: Deaconess Medical Center Skilled Nursing Center, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 28)
  - Great Falls: Park Place Health Care Center, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 3 / 29)
  - Hamilton: Marcus Daly Memorial Hospital, 1972-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 30)
  - Hamilton: Ravalli County Public Health Nursing Service, 1966-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 31)
  - Hamilton: Valley View Estates Nursing Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 32)
  - Hardin: Big Horn County Memorial Hospital and Nursing Home, 1971-1974, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 33)
  - Hardin: Heritage Acres, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 34)
  - Harlem: Harlem Rest Home, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Harlowton: Tri-Mountain Community Health Services (Home Health Agency), 1985-1987 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Harlowton: Wheatland Memorial Hospital and Nursing Home, 1971-1976, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
  - Havre: Lutheran Home of the Good Shepherd, 1964, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Havre: Northern Montana Hospital Home Health Agency, 1978-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Helena: Cedar Street Home (West-Mont Community Care, Inc.), 1980-1983 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Helena: Cooney Convalescent Home, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - Helena: Counseling Consortium, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Helena: Helena Nursing Home and Health Facilities, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Helena: Independent Home Health Care, Inc., 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Helena: St. Peter's Community Hospital, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
  - Helena: Shodair Children's Hospital, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Helena: Veterans Administration Hospital, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - Helena: Western Care Nursing Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 14-15)
  - Helena: West-Mont Community Care / Home Health Care, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
  - Hot Springs: Hot Springs Convalescent, Inc., 1984-1987 (Box-folder 4 / 17)
  - Jordan: Garfield County Hospital / Health Center (hospital and nursing home), 1972-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
  - Kalispell: Brendan House, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 19)
  - Kalispell: Flathead County Home Health Agency, 1966-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 20)
  - Kalispell: Flathead County Nursing Home, 1970-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 21)
  - Kalispell: Glacier View Hospital, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 22)
  - Kalispell: Immanuel Lutheran Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 23)
  - Kalispell: Kalispell General Hospital / Kalispell Regional Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 24)
  - Lewistown: Central Montana Hospital Home Health Program, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 4 / 25)
  - Lewistown: Central Montana Personal Care Home, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 26)
  - Lewistown: Montana Center for the Aged, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 27)
  - Lewistown: St. Joseph's Hospital and Nursing Home / Central Montana Hospital and Nursing Home, 1969-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 28)
  - Lewistown: Valle Vista Manor, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 4 / 29)
  - Libby: Libby Convalescent Center / Libby Care Center, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 30)
  - Libby: St. John's Lutheran Hospital, 1962, 1971-1984 (Box-folder 4 / 31)
  - Livingston: Livingston Convalescent Center, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 32)
  - Livingston: Livingston Memorial Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4 / 33)
  - Livingston: Park County Home Health Agency, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 4 / 34)
  - Malta: Phillips County Good Samaritan Retirement Center, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Malta: Phillips County Hospital Association, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Miles City: Abbey (Maternity) Hospital / Abbey Convalescent Home, 1947-1968 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
  - Miles City: Custer County Rest Home, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Miles City: Friendship Villa, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Miles City: Holy Rosary Home Health Service, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - Miles City: Holy Rosary Hospital, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Miles City: Veterans Administration, 1978 (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - Missoula: Heritage Hearth Personal Care, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 9)
  - Missoula: Hillside Manor, 1969-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
  - Missoula: Maplewood Manor, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 5 / 11)
  - Missoula: Missoula City-County Home Health Agency, 1966-1983 (Box-folder 5 / 12)
  - Missoula: Missoula Community Hospital, 1967-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
  - Missoula: Missoula Community Hospital Home Health Agency, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 14)
  - Missoula: Missoula Crippled Children and Adults Rehabilitation Center / Missoula Rehabilitation Center (home health agency), 1978-1981 (Box-folder 5 / 15)
  - Missoula: Missoula General Hospital, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 5 / 16)
  - Missoula: Mountain View Extended Care and Nursing Home Facility / Community Nursing and Rehabilitation Facility, 1972-1988 (Box-folder 5 / 17)
  - Missoula: Mountain West Home Health Services, Inc., 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 18)
  - Missoula: Royal Manor, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 19)
  - Missoula: St. Patrick's Hospital, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 5 / 20)
  - Missoula: Wayside Nursing Home, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 21)
  - Philipsburg: Granite County Memorial Hospital, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 22)
  - Philipsburg: Granite County Memorial Nursing Home, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 23)
  - Plains: Clark Fork Valley Home Health Agency, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 24)
  - Plains: Clark Fork Valley Hospital, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 25)
  - Plains: Clark Fork Valley Nursing Home, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 26)
  - Plentywood: Sheridan Memorial Home Health Agency, 1985 (Box-folder 5 / 27)
  - Plentywood: Sheridan Memorial Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 28)
  - Plentywood: Sheridan Memorial Nursing Home, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 29)
  - Polson: Lake County Home Health Agency, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 30)
  - Polson: St. Joseph Convalescent Center, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 5 / 31)
  - Polson: St. Joseph Home Health Care Agency, 1977-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 32)
  - Polson: St. Joseph Hospital, 1966-1980 (Box-folder 5 / 33)
  - Poplar: Poplar Community Hospital and Nursing Home, 1976, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 34)
  - Red Lodge: Carbon County Health Care Center, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 35)
  - Red Lodge: Carbon County Memorial Hospital, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 36)
  - Red Lodge: Carbon County Memorial Nursing Home, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 37)
  - Ronan: Happy Acres Rest Home, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 38)
  - Ronan: St. Luke Community Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 39)
  - Ronan: St. Luke Community Nursing Home, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 40)
  - Ronan: West Side Rest Home, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 41)
  - Roundup: Roundup Memorial Hospital, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 42)
  - Roundup: Roundup Memorial Nursing Home, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 43)
  - St. Ignatius: Mission Valley Hospital, 1977-1979, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 44)
  - Scobey: Daniels Memorial Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 45)
  - Scobey: Daniels Memorial Hospital Home Health Agency, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 5 / 46)
  - Scobey: Daniels Memorial Nursing Home, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 47)
  - Shelby: Toole County Home Health Agency, 1986 (Box-folder 5 / 48)
  - Shelby: Toole County Hospital, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 49)
  - Shelby: Toole County Nursing Home, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 50)
  - Sheridan: Madison County Nursing Home, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Sheridan: Ruby Valley Hospital, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Sheridan: Ruby Valley Hospital Home Health Agency, 1986 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - Sidney: Community Memorial Hospital, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
  - Sidney: Richland County Health Department Home Health Agency / Nursing Care in the Home, 1966-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - Sidney: Richland Homes, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Stevensville: Bitterroot Home Health, Inc., 1985-1988 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
  - Stevensville: North Valley Nursing Home, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
  - Superior: Mineral County Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Superior: Mineral County Nursing Home, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
  - Terry: Prairie Community Hospital, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
  - Terry: Prairie Community Nursing Home, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
  - Townsend: Broadwater Community Hospital, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
  - Townsend: Broadwater Health Center, 1975-1978, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
  - Warm Springs: Montana State Hospital, Building 219, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
  - White Sulphur Springs: Mountainview Memorial Hospital, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
  - White Sulphur Springs: Mountainview Memorial Nursing Home, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6 / 17)
  - Whitefish: Colonial Manor Nursing Home, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 18)
  - Whitefish: North Valley Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 19)
  - Whitefish: North Valley Hospital Extended Care Center, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 6 / 20)
  - Wibaux: Wibaux County Nursing Home, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 21)
  - Wolf Point: Faith Lutheran Home, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 22)
  - Wolf Point: Trinity Hospital, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 23)
- Financial
  - Licensing registrars, 1947-1965 (Volume Vol. 1-2)
  - Items removed from volumes 1-2, undated (Box-folder 6 / 24)
- Miscellany
  - Forms on which surveys were conducted. Pink sheets in the case files are a extract of the deficiencies noted on these forms, and the follow up to them, undated (Box-folder 6 / 25)